[Music]
welcome to busy Center lunch event and
our session about what is new about V8
da in busy Center well my colleague pred
and Magnus together with me will try to
explain all new features related with
this topic but also clarify some of
them we will first start with reminding
why and how we started with this feature
and continue with some setup and
expected results based on this setup
then we will continue with uh showing
how to use this feature in practice but
also some development aspects of this
feature we will also introduce something
you asked and now we are planning to
deliver redesign of V date range as many
of you wanted it separate from posting
date range and you will also touch topic
about possible changing of f date after
posting okay let's
start uh first to remind how we started
this is um uh requirement from BC ideas
uh idea in basically was uh not to use
all the time posting date for V purpose
that we can choose a document date and
based on all this requirement we decided
to introduce new field V8
date okay a road map uh was that we
started with 2022 release Wave 2 or
version
21 and this is this is the moment when
we added these to production on the
first minor we uh made some update
adding V return limitations and after
that uh based on your feedback
especially from directions Yammer we
introducing few uh new features
limitations and some back
fixes so we will we continue with
upgrade grading and adding small
improvements based on all existing
feedbacks and internal fining in last
five to six months and now finally with
version
23 uh we as I said we listen your
feedback and you're required to change
this setup not to use a general ledger
setup for a l from to posting We decided
to move this to V allow from uh posting
it will come in next to min not
immediately in October but this is
definitely in our Clos road
map um let's remind you about basic
things of involving these new fields to
the entries in preparation for 2022
release W2 Microsoft run upgrade code to
populate V8 date in existing entries for
the posting date we did that because the
V date wasn't previously used in V
reporting so data transfer was used the
first time to populate this data
now what is important here this feature
is W1 feature so it means it is
available in all actually in most of
countries where busy Central is
available except Italy as Italy already
had similar feature there so in Italy it
is postponed
it
um in all those countries with existing
V functionality this field is named as
vat date but what is important to know
in localization without V system this
field still exists and this date is
referred to as tax date tax date
automatically use the posting date on a
document so it must have date even
customers do not see it that means you
will not see it but c will automatically
fill in this uh uh tax date uh based on
your posting
date okay let's now make a look at the
setup and results expected based on
different different setup
models first V dat
usage um to use V date feature the first
step is to choose enable in a vat date
usage field on a general ler setup
page enabling V date usage field um
makes V dat field available in all
relevant page it means in document page
in entries everywhere it is important to
know that except enabl there are two
other uh options for this field all
those options will not block uh the use
of 8 date these two other options are
accept enable we now have enable prevent
modification option which prevents user
from modify V8 date after document has
been posted that means this is more or
less the same your enable feature but if
this is only enabled you can do
everything you can change even date
after posting but if you have this
prevent modification you you will have
everything except possibility to change
V dat in the posting documents and this
is enabled by
default uh this exists especially
because some countries it is not allowed
to modify vat date after document have
be posted then disabled which hides all
instances of vat data across the
application but what is important to
remember V date will still be used and
automatically populated with posting
date it means if you choose disable it
will not be disabled as a feature you
will just not see V8 fi across
application but system will use posting
date by default in general there will
not be difference because previously
used all the C reports basing on posting
date now you will use based on V date
but this V date be exactly the same as a
posting
date um note that these options aren't
available in a country version where V
is not used and system will use posting
dat is default date in tax date field
but it means in general you will not see
this feature uh to enable this disabl
but this feature will be disabled
automatically and system will populate
the text date with posting
date uh what is additionally important
here if the feature is enabled you can
enter the V date on theant page but
however if left empty it will be
populated with default date you will see
later in some
examples now uh default date the default
V date field defines whether the posting
date or document date are used as a
fault value again they're talking only
about default date as it can be changed
in not posting documents and it will
have an impact about some postings as
well and as I said you will see it
later and now if you use V period in B
Central the control V period setup field
controls whether to check and
potentially block posting in V date is
defined with Clos
periods in those cases the following
happens uh this is because these
settings ensure consistency in vort
reporting and prevent uh posed documents
with an empty V8 date but with this
control you can prevent or eventually
warning having new posting entries
within closed and close or and release
V8 period and of course you can disable
this setup at all if you do not use the
periods now my colleague Magnus will
show you how to use this feature in a
practice and the list of available
reports where V date appears
Magnus
thank you Alexander so let's take a a
brief moment to have an overview of how
V date Works in business
Central so as Alexander nicely explained
we have on the general ledger setup
default vat date field which controls
whether vat date should default to
posting date or document date and this
is used to aop populate the field on a
document that you might create if you
want you can of course edit V date if
needed
and then when posting We copy the date
onto the posted document and the related
entries such as vat entries and G
entries let's look at what happens in
case that the vat date is not
populated during the posting routine we
will again use the setup from general
ledger setup the default V date to
actually take the posting date and copy
onto the vat date in case this was the
setting that you have and then as before
or this will just be copied onto the
posted
document we also updated some V based
reports among those are the V statement
the calculate and post V settlement vat
Vice declaration and many more in both
W1 and local reports the important thing
to note here is that with the default
setup in the system there are not going
to be any changes to these reports or
their output posting date and vat date
will be the same and it's only in the
case that you manually edit V date on a
document or change the setup that these
reports might produce different
results and now I will hand it over to
my colleague pric who will go more in
detail with vat thank you Manus we saw
how to enable and set up vat date in
business Central that can be used for
vat related reports this report
summarize V related transaction and
assist user in complying with local tax
regulation to ensure that the reports
are accurate we needed to guarantee that
transactions are correctly filtered in
these reports based on their V dates
this bring us to the V date consistency
check that we implemented in the posting
procedure we Define three
checks the first one is about Define a
default vat date if it is empty the
second one is to ensure that V date is
within allow vat posting data
range and third one is to ensure that
vat date is within not close V return
periods I will trying to explain the
reasons for introducing those and how
they are implemented in the next few
minutes this is an overview of how the
posting process works in regard to V
date our approach was to design it on
that way to provide High level of
flexibility for partners to set it up
while also considering different
localization aspects in the first step
for every document type we check whether
V date is defined while it is impossible
to post issue or release document with
the blank V date from user interface
there is possibility to do that using
apis therefore we introduce this check
and if the vat is blank BC will default
it according to the general ledger setup
next we have V allowed uh periods and if
the vat date Falls outside of defined
period posting procedure would be
aborted finally we need to ensure that
no new posting are completed within
close vat return periods or provide
warning in cases when V period is
released or
submitted I would like to take a few
minutes to clarify how we handle
defaulting the V date many users Express
the expectation that setting the field V
date usage to disabled would prevent its
usage
entirely however it is crucial to
understand that V date is from
compliance standpoint indispensible and
cannot be disabled V date should be
considered as a tax date and it is used
in all localization primarily for
reporting
purposes given this significance of V
date we have taken steps to ensure that
every Cod involved in posting procedure
in includes check for the vat date on
this slide you can see simple procedure
that is implemented in the code units
above in cases where V date is left
blank we have implemented a mechanism to
defaulty to the value defined in the GL
setup this ensur that compliance
requirements are consistently met and
there are no gaps in the handling of the
V
date let's now take a look on allowed V
date periods following the similar
principle from implementing allowed
posting dates in general ledger setup we
implemented similar functionality for V
date the idea is to allow administrators
to Define periods of time during which
specified users are able to post the
code here is simple we use is handle
pattern to allow Partners to change
behavior and then verify V
date what is important also to mention
that in the initial version we used
existing Fields allowed posting from and
allowed posting to from the general
ledger setup to verify vat date 2 based
on your feedback we decided to split it
in the version
23 uh it will be released in one of
minor versions so now we have the same
Fields used to check vat date only
defined in vat
setup how it will work to ensure
seamless transition from our current for
our current user the upate code will
copy the existing values from the
general ledger setup to the vat setup
Fields the existing posting date check
um remains unchanged but we are uh
enhancing flexibility and V date control
as these fields will be exclusively used
for verifying vat
date finally our priority is to prevent
any new posting with v date within
closed V return periods or in cases
where the V return is released or
submitted issue a
warning the V return can have various
statuses from open accepted closed to
cancelled and our aim here is to protect
users from posting documents that would
result with non-compliance situation
that would require additional effort to
fix the
problem using general ledger setup field
control vat date um it is possible to
handle these cases from blocking posting
providing warning to ignore
it with that I will pass to monus who
will continue explaining how you can
modify V date after posting the
documents thank you prodct all right so
let's take a look at if you might need
to change V date after having posted a
document we allow you to do this from
the vat entries where you can go to a
record and specify a new vat date but
only if your setup allows you to do so
as nicely explained by
Alexander once saved this date will then
be propagated to posted document as well
as related GL entries based on
transaction number document number
document type and posting
date and now I will hand it off to
Alexander to conclude this session okay
Magus thank you and um yeah we we finish
this session for today I would like to
say thank you uh for all of you who
watching this session and I would like
to invite you to for q& a session Q&A
session is planned for October 11 you
will find more information on a portal
so you are more than welcome to ask more
questions about these features before I
finish with um this session I would like
to invite you for some other sessions
and all of them if I'm not wrong 35 of
them are there and all of them are
really good good about new features but
I would like to take this opportunity to
invite you uh something more related
with localization and legislation topics
what is new legislation localization and
again something really important for the
most of countries introduction to new
electronic invoicing or electronic
document uh module this is something
really important and it will be used
much more in future before I close again
there are a lot of interesting and
important URLs about uh busy Center so
you can use some of them to find
interesting information if you cannot
uh remember all of them please do not
forget this AK msbc all so you can find
all interest information there so on the
end thank you in M and P mag
name